48. Victorian Art From 1837 to 1901, Queen Victoria ruled England.
She ruled while the British Empire became the most powerful, most modern, and wealthiest
nation in the world. For this reason, many people of that era were very positive. They
believed science could solve the world's problems. They believed their empire was changing the
world for the better. Their new wealth and positive outlook led to an explosion of new
artwork, as people had time to make, think about, and consume art. The Victorian age gave us new
styles of painting. One was called pre-Raphaelite. The pre-Raphaelites believed that after Raphael
and Michelangelo, art became too controlled. They believed emotion and rich details were more
important than reason and rules of composition. They thought paintings should explode with color
and feeling. Their paintings were richly colored and very detailed. Dante Rossetti and William
Holman Hunt are typical pre-Raphaelite painters. Romanticism was similar to the pre-Raphaelite
movement, in that it valued emotion over reason. The Romanticists were fascinated by nature,
their heroic and beautiful, and the dark and diseased. They used scenes from the Middle Ages,
because they believed that was a darker, more passionate time than the popular classical period.
They focused on amazing individuals rather than social rules. Another important development in
Victorian art was the beginning of photography. Queen Victoria was the first monarch to have her
photo taken. This new technology was being used for science and art. Many early photos are composed
like paintings, while others explore the differences between the art forms. The energy and emotions of
the Victorian age brought many positive changes. People pushed the boundaries of their art and
technology and created new styles and new ideas. They still influence us today.